<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: xcode | Learn-a-holic Geek Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://learnaholic.me/categories/xcode/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://learnaholic.me/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-29T04:34:56+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://learnaholic.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kornelije Sajler]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[xajler@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Xcode 4.5: Source Version Control wit Git and Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://learnaholic.me/2012/11/29/xcode-4-dot-5-source-version-control-wit-git-and-github/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-29T04:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://learnaholic.me/2012/11/29/xcode-4-dot-5-source-version-control-wit-git-and-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OK, so we created the skeleton of App. While creating the <em>Xcode Project</em> we could add the project
to <em>Git</em> repository, but we didn't, we shall do it manually and finally at the end we shall
push it to the <em>Github</em> hosted repository.</p>

<h2>Git Repository</h2>

<p>Firstly we really want to add a proper <em>Xcode</em> and <em>Objective-C</em> <code>.gitignore</code> file. Here is the
<em>Gist</em> link to one proper <a href="https://gist.github.com/3786883">.gitingnore</a>. Download and copy
it to the App root, before doing the first commit or use <code>wget</code> as I did!</p>

<p>Since we didn't create the <em>Git</em> repository when the <em>Xcode</em> was offering. We shall create
repository, add <code>.gitignore</code> and create initial commit:</p>

<p><code>
wget https://raw.github.com/gist/3786883/93e8364b202f691abc4cf3e22001a45e799011cc/.gitignore
git init .
git add .
git status
git commit -m 'Initial commit'
</code></p>

<p><img src="/images/02-01.png"></p>

<blockquote><p>Note</p>

<p>I would recommend creating repository without <em>Xcode</em> help. Because it will create no <code>.gitignore</code>
and by it will commit a lot of junk to repository.</p>

<p>Folders like <code>xcuserdata</code> will change frequently and polluting your
repository with not needed files and even more in teams, it can overwrite another developer's
<code>xcuserdata</code>  every time with not wanted user data from other developer!</p></blockquote>

<h2>XCode Organizer</h2>

<p>The <em>Xcode Organizer</em> is where the <em>Repositories</em> can be viewed.</p>

<blockquote><p>Note</p>

<p>If you had a <em>Xcode</em> open during the creation of repository through Terminal, reopen the
the <em>Xcode</em> because it will not detect the repository in <em>Organizer</em>.</p></blockquote>

<p>To open <em>Organizer</em> go to <code>Window &gt; Organizer</code> or with keyboard shortcut <strong>⇧ ⌘ 2</strong>.
There should be a repository <em>Casa</em>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/02-02.png"></p>

<h2>Add Github Remote</h2>

<p>To add the <em>Github</em> remote so that we can push the commits to it, we first need to create
a <em>Github</em> repository, I've already created repository <a href="https://github.com/xajler/casa-app-xcode">casa-app-xcode</a>.</p>

<p>Let's add this remote with <em>Xcode</em>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Go to <em>Organizer Repositories</em>.</li>
<li>Select <em>Casa</em> repository.</li>
<li>In <em>Casa</em> repository select <em>Remotes</em>.</li>
<li>Hit the <code>Add Remote</code> circled plus button.</li>
<li>For <em>Remote Name</em> enter: <code>casa-app-xcode</code>.</li>
<li>For <em>Location</em> enter: <code>https://github.com/xajler/casa-app-xcode</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Ignore the git username and password if you have <em>Github SSH</em> set up.</p>

<p><img src="/images/02-03.png"></p>

<h2>Push changes to Github</h2>

<ul>
<li>Choose <code>File &gt; Source Control &gt; Push...</code>.</li>
<li>Wait availe for first time.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/02-04.png"></p>

<p>The commit is pushed to <em>Githb</em>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/02-05.png"></p>

<h2>Commiting changes with Xcode</h2>

<p>From the main app delegate <code>MIAppDelegate.m</code> we shall remove the generated comments and
commit it with Xcode:</p>

<ul>
<li>Applay changes to the <code>MIAppDelegate.m</code> by removing commented code in methods.</li>
<li>Commit it by going to <code>File &gt; Source Control &gt; Commit...</code> or use keyboard <strong>⌥ ⌘ C</strong>.</li>
<li>Enter the commit message.</li>
<li>Hit the <code>Commit 1 File</code> button.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/02-06.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Push changes to <a href="https://github.com/xajler/casa-app-xcode">Github repository</a>.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Branching in Xcode</h2>

<p>On commit it can be chosen to commit to branch with button <code>Commit to Branch...</code>. Where
the branch can be chosen or even newly one created.</p>

<p>Alternatively branches can be created in <em>Organizer Repositories</em> by selecting wanted
repository and selecting <em>Branches</em>, and hitting <code>Add Branch</code> button.</p>

<h2>Diff in Xcode</h2>

<p>Anytime while coding the <em>Version editor</em> can be turned on to see changes with current <code>HEAD</code>
but also it is possible to change to past revisions.</p>

<p><em>Xcode Version editor</em> is really nice and with visuals that helping in better understanding of the code changes.</p>

<p><img src="/images/02-07.png"></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>As I said in last post <em>Xcode 4</em> is great IDE, filled with lots of features. Respect to
have <em>Git</em> as default Version control. The <em>SVN</em> is also supported, but who would want to use
it in 21st Century. But in my opinion the Diff part is the greatest feature of it all!</p>

<p>But with all of this, I'm still not impressed with managing <em>Git</em> with IDE, and I will
still be using my favorite <em>iTerm2</em> to interact with <em>Git</em> and <em>Github</em>.</p>

<h2>What's next</h2>

<p>So we past the <em>Xcode</em> project creation (from ground up!) and in this post the Version Control
as <em>Git</em> and creating remote to the <em>Github</em>.</p>

<p>In next <em>Xcode</em> post we will have an broad overview of <em>Xcode</em> support of Testing. What
Testing Frameworks are available, which is the default <em>Xcode</em> Testing Framework.</p>

<p>Look for the <em>BDD</em> Testing Frameworks and picking one for more in depth examine of it. And also
the available Mocking Frameworks and its usage.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Xcode 4.5: Workspace, Project and Target Setup from Scratch]]></title>
    <link href="http://learnaholic.me/2012/11/28/xcode-4-dot-5-workspace-project-and-target-from-scratch/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-28T10:35:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://learnaholic.me/2012/11/28/xcode-4-dot-5-workspace-project-and-target-from-scratch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In aim to learn more about <em>Apple</em>'s Development stack and because I will be creating an
<em>iPhone</em> and will include <em>iPad</em> App as <code>Universal</code> App. I'll be going through creation of
the minimal as possible project setup for current stable version of <em>Xcode 4.5.2</em> and <em>iOS 6</em>.</p>

<h2>Workspace</h2>

<p>So first, what exactly is a <em>Workspace</em>, as I remember it was introduced with <em>Xcode</em> 4, and it
is a simply a container for combining multiple projects if they are needed, if not only <em>Project</em>
will due. But in our case, we know that we shall have multiple projects, so the <em>Workspace</em> is way to go.</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Note</strong></p>

<p>Maybe the desired workflow by <em>Apple</em> was first to create a <em>Project</em> and then if there is
need for another project to bundle them into <em>Workspace</em>. But I wanted show the hierarchical
structure of <em>Xcode</em> project, so on the top is a <em>Workspace</em> then <em>Project</em>.</p></blockquote>

<p>Create it by:</p>

<ul>
<li>First create a folder (with Finder or Terminal), name it whatever the App will be called in my case <em>Casa</em>.</li>
<li>Create <em>Workspace</em> by going to <code>File &gt; New &gt; Workspace...</code> or better with the keyboard key <strong>⌃ ⌘ N</strong>.</li>
<li>Enter desired name, in my case <code>Casa</code> and save it to <em>Casa</em> folder already created.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/01-01.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>It will create <em>Workspace</em> as folder named <code>Casa.xcworkspace</code>.</li>
<li>Do not close the <em>Workspace</em> or <em>Xcode</em> for now.</li>
</ul>


<blockquote><p><strong>Geek Tip</strong></p>

<p>For hard-core coders open <em>Xcode</em> and <em>Workspace</em> from <em>Terminal</em> with <code>open Casa.xcworkspace</code>.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Empty Project</h2>

<p>The <em>Xcode</em> project is the thing that is usually what it is created in most examples.
This way <em>Project</em> and the <em>Target(s)</em> will be created together.</p>

<p>But not to get the ahead of myself, we will not use this pattern, since we broke it with
creation of <em>Workspace</em> in first place, we will broke it even more by creating empty project.</p>

<p>Because when you start with the <em>Empty Project</em> you can actually see what <em>Project</em> is, basically
nothing, just another container, that will hold <em>Targets</em>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create <em>Empty Project</em> by going to <code>File &gt; New &gt; Project...</code> or by keyboard shortcut <strong>⇧ ⌘ N</strong>.</li>
<li>Something strange will happen, another instance of <em>Xcode</em> will open!!!</li>
<li>From <em>iOS</em> group choose <em>Other</em> in left pane and in right pane choose <em>Empty</em> as blue <em>Project</em> icon.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/01-02.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Hit the <code>Next</code> button, add <em>Product Name</em>, in my case, still <em>Casa</em>.</li>
<li>Again hit <code>Next</code> button, go to <em>Casa</em> folder, because we want the project to be created there.</li>
<li>Uncheck the <em>Create local git repository for this project</em>, we will set it later.</li>
<li>And for <em>Add to</em> we want to add it to <em>Casa Workspace</em> so choose <em>Casa</em>.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/01-03.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>It will close this instance of <em>Xcode</em>, but second instance will have a <em>Workspace</em> and <em>Project</em> all together!</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/01-04.png"></p>

<h2>Target (Empty Application)</h2>

<p>So finally we're getting to the meat of <em>Xcode</em>, the <em>Target</em> is what will hold all you code, resources,
settings for build or deployment. If we had not chosen <em>Empty Project</em> in last part,
it would create <em>Project</em> and <em>Target</em> all together, even if we chose the <em>Empty Application</em>.</p>

<p>But we are learning all the parts so we shall in this case create a simple as possible <em>Target</em>
for <em>iOS</em> - <em>Empty Application</em>.</p>

<ul>
<li>Make sure the <code>Casa</code> <em>Project</em> is selected and at bottom hit a big plus button <code>Add Target</code>.</li>
<li>In <em>iOS</em> group choose <em>Application</em> on left and on the right choose <em>Empty Application</em>. Hit <code>Next</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/01-05.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>For <em>Product Name</em> we will add, you guessed it: <em>Casa</em>.</li>
<li>Add the <em>Organization Name</em> and <em>Company Identifier</em>.</li>
<li>I tend to add <em>Class Prefix</em> (<code>MI</code> as <em>Metaintellect</em>), because there is no namespacing in <code>Objective-C</code>.</li>
<li>Depending what are you targeting, you'll choose <em>Devices</em>, I'm feeling lucky so I'm going with hardest <code>Universal</code> (iPhone and iPad support).</li>
<li><em>ARC (Automatic Reference Counting)</em> should be left checked!</li>
<li><em>Include Unit Test</em> should be unchecked, because we will set it later, from ground up!</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/01-06.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Hit <code>Finish</code> button and we have a target created.</li>
<li>Build it by <code>Project &gt; Build</code> or with <strong>⌘ B</strong> and we can ship it :)</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/01-07.png"></p>

<h2>My Thoughts on Objective-C</h2>

<p>So there are many ways to get to <em>AppStore</em> and not using the default <em>Apple</em> language: <em>Objective-C</em>.
One of many are <em>RubyMotion</em> (<em>Ruby</em>), <em>MonoTouch</em> (<em>C#</em>), <em>PhoneGap</em> (<em>HTML</em>, <em>CSS</em>, <em>JS</em>),..., but
<em>Objective-C</em> is still used as preferred language.</p>

<p>There is a lot of criticism on <em>Objective-C</em> language, even though it is a <em>C</em> based language,
like <em>C++</em>, <em>Java</em> and <em>C#</em>. But those are kind of similar language where transition is very
easy, but transition to <em>Objective-C</em> is awkward, even more than to <em>JavaScript</em>. And this
is mostly because <em>Objective-C</em> has a not only strong legacy in <em>C</em> (static and procedural part) but
also in one of the underestimated language <em>Smalltalk</em> (dynamic and object or better message driven part).</p>

<p>And even though the <em>Objective-C</em> looks very awkward, but because it has a legacy from two great
languages that are in my opinion pretty hard and crazy to merge, has my everlasting respect. And I
find my self writing <em>Objective-C</em> better and with more joy than the <em>Java</em> or <em>C#</em>.</p>

<p>What I dislike about the <em>Objective-C</em> is that code snippets, examples found on web are mostly so
poorly written, and same for most paid Video Tutorials. So much repetitive code, huge methods,
<strong>copy-paste driven development</strong> everywhere, same as in most <em>.NET</em> (especially VB.NET), <em>PHP</em>,
and also in <em>Rails</em> (excluding pure <em>Ruby</em> programmers) examples!</p>

<p>There is quite a lot resources how to create <em>iOS</em> apps but mainly focusing on the features
like Table Views, MapKit, and so on. But it is really hard to find good source on
Design Patterns, refactoring and best coding practices, or how to structure the <em>iOS</em>
app into Groups (there are no Folders, files are all in root of <em>Target</em>).</p>

<p>But there are quite neat features in <em>Objective-C</em> features like protocols and categories.
I also like the progress or evolution of <em>Objective-C</em> for embracing properties, <em>ARC</em> (Automatic
Reference Counting), Blocks, GCD (Grand Central Dispatch) and new literals for Arrays, Dictionaries,...</p>

<p>And for the end abandoning the old <em>GCC</em> compiler and embracing and involving in creating
<em>LLVM</em> compiler, much faster, and now with really great code inspection built in to <em>Xcode</em>...</p>

<h2>My Thoughts on Xcode 4</h2>

<p>And there is <em>Xcode</em>, the version 3 was too funky too me, especially separate <em>Interface Builder</em>
and Apple old-school floating inspectors and controls all around the desktop.</p>

<p>Bet then came the version 4 and even though I really dislike the IDEs, must admit that it is to me
the best IDE. Especially comparing to <em>Eclipse</em> and <em>Visual Studio</em>. Responsiveness is great,
integration with <em>Git</em> (even though I still prefer using it by Terminal) and diff viewer
is really what was expected of Apple, also <em>StoryBoard</em> and integrated <em>Inerface Builder</em>.
Multi monitor friendly, assistant editor, help integrated, I think you get it, the best IDE I've
worked! Don't get me wrong there is still place for improvements but in my opinion <em>Apple</em> is on the
right track.</p>

<h2>What's Next</h2>

<p>In next post we'll examine <em>Xcode</em> SCM (Source Control Management) capabilities using built-in
support for <em>Git</em>. Also we'll push this project to <em>GitHub</em>, examine <em>Xcode</em> <em>Git</em> Diffing and History.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
